<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<addon id="plugin.audio.soundcloud" name="SoundCloud" version="5.9.0" provider-name="TheWorms">
    <requires>
        <import addon="xbmc.python" version="3.0.0"/>
        <import addon="script.module.requests" version="2.29.0"/>
        <!-- Pillow (PIL fork) is used to generate the blurred cover art
             background and extract the dominant colour for the
             "Now Playing" fullscreen overlay (waveform / cinema styles).
             Marked optional="true" so the addon still loads and works
             on Kodi installs where script.module.pil is missing
             (notably some Android builds) — the overlays gracefully
             fall back to unblurred covers in that case. -->
        <import addon="script.module.pil" version="1.0.0" optional="true"/>
    </requires>
    <extension point="xbmc.python.pluginsource" library="addon.py">
        <provides>audio</provides>
    </extension>
    <extension point="xbmc.python.script" library="script.py">
        <provides>audio</provides>
    </extension>
    <extension point="xbmc.addon.metadata">
        <summary lang="de_DE">SoundCloud – Musik- und Podcast-Streaming-Plattform</summary>
        <summary lang="en_GB">SoundCloud – Music and podcast streaming platform</summary>
        <summary lang="fr_FR">SoundCloud – Plateforme de streaming musical et de podcasts</summary>
        <summary lang="nl_NL">SoundCloud – Muziek- en podcaststreamingplatform</summary>
        <description lang="de_DE">SoundCloud ist eine Musik- und Podcast-Streaming-Plattform, mit der Du Millionen von Songs aus der ganzen Welt anhören kannst.</description>
		<description lang="en_GB">SoundCloud is a music and podcast streaming platform that lets you listen to millions of songs from around the world.</description>
        <description lang="fr_FR">SoundCloud est une plateforme de streaming musical et de podcasts qui vous permet d'écouter des millions de titres du monde entier.</description>
        <description lang="nl_NL">SoundCloud is een muziek- en podcaststreamingplatform waarmee je naar miljoenen nummers van over de hele wereld kunt luisteren.</description>
        <disclaimer lang="en_GB">This plugin is not official, approved or endorsed by SoundCloud.</disclaimer>
        <disclaimer lang="fr_FR">Ce plugin n'est pas officiel, approuvé ou soutenu par SoundCloud.</disclaimer>
        <disclaimer lang="nl_NL">Deze plugin is niet officieel, goedgekeurd of gesteund door SoundCloud.</disclaimer>
        <platform>all</platform>
        <license>MIT</license>
        <forum>https://forum.kodi.tv/showthread.php?tid=206635</forum>
        <website>https://soundcloud.com</website>
        <source>https://github.com/jaylinski/kodi-addon-soundcloud</source>
        <credits>jaylinski (original add-on), bromix, SLiX</credits>
        <news>5.9.0 (2026-04-29) - Vinyl style + complete spec
New "Vinyl" fullscreen overlay! Editorial-vinyl layout: a detailed black vinyl record on the left half (with the cover art embedded in the central label), title and artist on the right. The disc rotates continuously at 33⅓ RPM (one turn every 12 seconds) — both the record and the cover label rotate together as a rigid unit so the cover stays oriented with the disc.

The vinyl PNG is generated at build time with subtle concentric grooves, a diagonal light reflection sweep, rim highlights, and a transparent label hole that reveals the cover art underneath.

Performance note: continuous rotation animations may stutter on lower-end devices (Raspberry Pi 3 etc.). If you experience this, please report and we'll add a "static disc" toggle.

This release completes the full 5-style fullscreen overlay spec: Off / Cinema / Waveform / Editorial / Vinyl.

5.8.9 (2026-04-29) - editorial: no fallback metadata
The Editorial pull quote area is now left empty when the track has no description, instead of falling back to "Genre · Year" or "...". Empty whitespace reads as intentional editorial restraint; fake filler doesn't.

5.8.8 (2026-04-29) - Editorial fullscreen style
New "Editorial" fullscreen overlay! A magazine-style layout with the cover art on the left third and large display typography on the right two-thirds. Pulls a clean version of the track's SoundCloud description and uses it as a pull quote (URLs and trailing hashtag chains are stripped, content is truncated to ~280 characters at a sentence boundary). Falls back to genre + year if no description is available.

Honest note on typography: Kodi's Python WindowXML system does NOT allow addons to register their own TTF fonts (documented limitation). Times New Roman bundled with the addon would not work. The editorial feel is therefore achieved through layout, sizing, letter-spacing and rule lines using only the standard Kodi font names — visually convincing but not actually serif. Sorry about the earlier promise.

5.8.7 (2026-04-29) - waveform becomes a visualizer
The Waveform overlay no longer uses the static SoundCloud waveform shape — instead 90 orange bars are continuously animated at 12 FPS to simulate a live audio visualizer. Bars on the left move slowly with medium amplitude (bass), middle ones vary fast and tall (mids), right ones flicker quickly with smaller amplitude (highs). The result LOOKS audio-reactive even though Kodi's Python API doesn't expose actual audio samples.

A thin orange progress bar above the visualizer shows the real playback position based on Player.Time, so users still have an accurate playback indicator.

5.8.6 (2026-04-28) - waveform bars now actually colour orange
Reverted to the dual-bar approach (grey background + orange foreground stacked, foreground hidden by default). Python now flips visibility of the orange bars as the track plays, instead of using setColorDiffuse which is silently no-op on some Kodi/skin combinations (notably Arctic Zephyr Reloaded).

5.8.5 (2026-04-28) - hide unimplemented styles
Removed "Vinyl" and "Editorial" from the fullscreen style picker — they were silently doing nothing because their XML+Python isn't done yet. They'll come back when implemented in 5.8.6+. The picker now shows only Off / Cinema / Waveform.

5.8.4 (2026-04-28) - simpler waveform XML
Halved the number of waveform bar controls (from 180 to 90) by using setColorDiffuse to switch played bars from grey to orange instead of stacking two image controls per position. This may have been the reason the waveform overlay wouldn't open on some Kodi builds — too many controls. Removed the dedicated background image control too, the cover art is shown directly (dimmed) when Pillow isn't installed.

5.8.3 (2026-04-28) - Pillow dependency + diagnostic
Declared Pillow (script.module.pil) as an OPTIONAL dependency in addon.xml so Kodi proposes its installation automatically when missing. The addon still loads without it (overlays fall back to unblurred covers).

Added detailed logging in NowPlayingDialog and PlayerObserver to diagnose cases where the fullscreen overlay doesn't appear. Look for "NowPlayingDialog onInit" and "_maybe_open_now_playing" in kodi.log.

5.8.2 (2026-04-28) - Waveform fullscreen style
New "Waveform" fullscreen overlay style — the SoundCloud signature look. Set Settings > Playback > Fullscreen on playback > Style to "Waveform" to enable.

Features: blurred cover art as fullscreen background (real Gaussian blur via Pillow if installed, fallback to dimmed cover otherwise), 90 vertical bars showing the actual track waveform downloaded from SoundCloud's waveform JSON, bars turn from grey to orange as the track plays, smooth Ken Burns zoom on background, slide-in title and artist.

Requires Pillow (script.module.pil from the Kodi addon repository) for the best visual experience. Without Pillow the dialog still works but uses the unblurred cover and a fallback dominant colour.

5.8.1 (2026-04-28) - opaque mask for fullscreen overlay
The Cinema overlay now has a solid black background as its first layer, fully masking the home UI underneath. Previously the home UI was visible "showing through" the dialog because WindowXMLDialog draws over the existing window without hiding it.

5.8.0 (2026-04-27) - fullscreen overlay (Cinema style)
New "Now Playing" fullscreen overlay! When audio playback starts, a custom dialog can open on top of the home UI showing the cover art with Ken Burns animation, title, artist, time and an orange progress bar.

Configure via Settings > Playback > Fullscreen on playback. Available styles in this release: "Cinema" (Apple Music / Spotify style with blurred background and centred cover) and "Off" (no overlay). Other styles (Waveform, Vinyl, Editorial) coming in 5.8.x.

Default is "Off" — opt in by changing the setting.

5.7.7 (2026-04-27) - widget detection improved + flash workaround documented
Improved widget vs user detection: now explicitly detects MyMusicNav.xml, musicfiles, addonbrowser, filemanager as user-browsing contexts. Previously relied on Window.IsActive(home) which gave false negatives in some Kodi builds. Diagnostic logs are still active to help debug edge cases.

The music-browser flash on launch can't be fully eliminated from inside the addon (Kodi renders the music page before calling the plugin), but the readme now documents how to bypass it entirely using a Kodi favourite or skin home shortcut that calls RunScript(plugin.audio.soundcloud) directly.

5.7.6 (2026-04-27) - aggressive flash hiding
Reordered the launch sequence and added Dialog.Close(all,true) before ReplaceWindow(home) — the "music addons" page is now closed immediately along with any modal dialog spinner before our UI launches, reducing the music-window flash to near-invisible.

5.7.5 (2026-04-26) - token resilience + diagnostics
The token is no longer disabled on the FIRST 401 response. SoundCloud occasionally returns transient 401s for valid tokens (network blips, rate limits, backend deploys), and the previous code was way too aggressive. Now we wait for 2 consecutive 401s before disabling the token, and the counter resets on any successful authenticated call.

Also added detailed logging for every authenticated API call: endpoint, status code, response time, token call count and lifetime tracking. When a 401 finally hits, the log shows how long the token actually lived and how many calls it served — making it possible to diagnose the real cause of token expiry.

Tests for the new behaviour added (28 tests now passing).

5.7.4 (2026-04-26) - hide music window flash
When opening the addon from Music > Add-ons, Kodi briefly shows the music browser before our full-screen UI takes over. Now we call ReplaceWindow(home) right before launching the script, so the music window is replaced (not stacked) — the flash is invisible and Back from the UI goes straight to home instead of bouncing back to the music browser.

5.7.3 (2026-04-26) - diagnostic
Logs detailed window/context info on every root call so we can identify why the widget/UI auto-detection fails on Arctic Zephyr Reloaded. Look for "ROOT context diag" lines in kodi.log.

5.7.2 (2026-04-26) - smart UI auto-launch
Auto-detect whether the addon is being called by a skin home widget (data fetch — return a directory) or by the user clicking the addon (open the full UI). Detection is based on whether the Kodi Home screen is active. Fixes the regression where users had to click "▶ Open SoundCloud" every time after 5.7.1.

5.7.1 (2026-04-26) - widget compatibility fix
Fixed: skin home widgets (Arctic Zephyr Reloaded, etc.) used to launch the full-screen UI when added — kicking the user out of their home screen. The addon root URL now returns a flat directory listing of widget shortcuts, so widgets show actual content. Users clicking on the addon from Kodi's add-on browser see a "▶ Open SoundCloud" entry as the first item to launch the full UI.

5.7.0 (2026-04-26) - simplification
Removed the classic plugin-style menu — the full-screen UI is now the only interface. Removes 75 lines of code, the "Auto-launch" setting, the ?legacy=1 escape hatch and the /launch-ui/ route. Skin home widgets continue to work via the dedicated /widget/* routes (independent of the menu). The "Off" option in Widget mode now shows the full UI instead of the classic menu.

5.6.1 (2026-04-26) - widget mode for Arctic Zephyr
Arctic Zephyr Reloaded only lets widgets point at the addon root, so the previous /widget/likes/ etc. routes weren't reachable through its UI. Added a "Widget mode" setting (Settings > Display > Skin home widget) that changes what the root returns. Pick Likes / Playlists / Following / Trending / Discover and the home widget will display that. Use ?legacy=1 to keep accessing the menu.

5.6.0 (2026-04-26) - skin widgets
Added 5 widget shortcut routes that any skin can target as a flat directory: /widget/likes/, /widget/playlists/, /widget/following/, /widget/trending/, /widget/discover/. A new "Widgets" entry in the classic plugin menu lets you browse them from a skin's "Add Widget" picker. See the readme for the Arctic Zephyr Reloaded setup procedure.

5.5.14 (2026-04-25) - progress bar fix v3
Progress bar updater is now started AFTER the GUI is built (in onInit) instead of in __init__ — that's why no setWidth() calls were being made. Added explicit logging so we can verify the thread is running and the values are being computed. Look for "ProgressUpdater" lines in kodi.log.

5.5.13 (2026-04-25) - progress bar v3
Progress bar now resized directly via Python control.setWidth() instead of relying on $INFO[Window.Property] in XML width (which Kodi doesn't re-evaluate per frame). The orange fill image has a fixed XML id and the background thread calls setWidth() every 500ms with the computed pixel width. This works regardless of skin or audio format.

5.5.12 (2026-04-25) - custom progress bar
Replaced the native Kodi progress bar (which was hijacked by Arctic Zephyr Reloaded's blue styling and frozen for HLS streams) with two stacked custom images. A background Python thread polls the player position every 500ms and updates the orange fill width via Window.Property. This fixes both the "always blue" and "never moves" issues at once.

5.5.11 (2026-04-25)
Time/Duration labels in the mini-player are now wider, brighter (white instead of grey), and use a bigger font (font12) so 1:23:45-style timestamps display fully without truncation
Removed unnecessary border attributes from progress bar that were causing rendering issues on some skins (orange.png is now a flat 1x1 pixel that Kodi stretches reliably)

NOTE: if the progress bar still doesn't move, check Settings > Playback > Audio format — set it to "Standard stable (MP3 progressive)" rather than "Standard adaptive (MP3 HLS)". HLS streams can prevent Player.Progress from updating on some Kodi builds.

5.5.10 (2026-04-25)
Updated readme.md with the new v5 interface description and a corrected, step-by-step OAuth token procedure (using the Authorization header, with explicit warnings about the cookie pitfall)

5.5.9 (2026-04-25)
Added TheWorms as a contributor (visible in Kodi's add-on info screen)

5.5.8 (2026-04-25) - progress bar fix
Fixed progress bar showing as fully filled and frozen: switched midtexture to use 9-patch border rendering and added explicit empty lefttexture/righttexture/overlaytexture so Kodi correctly interpolates the fill width
Resized orange.png from 4x4 to 8x8 so it survives the border="2" 9-patch slicing
Progress bar now shows in SoundCloud orange (#FF5500) and updates in real-time as the track plays

5.5.7 (2026-04-25)
Fixed: changes to OAuth token (or any setting) now take effect immediately without needing to restart Kodi
The Settings class now creates a fresh xbmcaddon.Addon() instance on every read, bypassing Kodi's in-memory cache that was hiding the new value
Auto-reset of the "token invalid" flag when the user changes the token — no more stuck 401 state after a paste

5.5.6 (2026-04-24) - diagnostic
"Test OAuth token" now shows the actual error body from SoundCloud (not just the HTTP code), and logs the full request + response details to kodi.log for debugging.

5.5.5 (2026-04-24)
OAuth token cleaning is now much more aggressive: strips ALL whitespace and non-printable characters anywhere in the token (not just leading/trailing). Catches Windows clipboard \r\n, zero-width spaces, BOM, etc. that were silently breaking authentication.
"Test OAuth token" now displays a token preview (length + first/last chars) so you can verify the paste was clean.

5.5.4 (2026-04-24)
Rewrote "How to get a token" help text — now correctly recommends the Authorization HTTP header (not the cookie). The cookie method silently fails, which is what was causing persistent 401 errors.

5.5.3 (2026-04-24)
After closing SoundCloud (Back), now go straight to Kodi home instead of bouncing back to the Music files / add-ons window
OAuth token field auto-strips "OAuth " or "Bearer " prefix if pasted by mistake (and surrounding quotes)

5.5.2 (2026-04-24)
Added "Test OAuth token" button in Settings > Account, right below the token field — verifies the token by calling /me and shows your username on success
Optimized /me handling: when the token is known invalid, skip the call entirely instead of doing 2 round-trips per UI page

5.5.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed cascade of HTTP 401 errors on public endpoints when an OAuth token is expired/invalid: the API now drops the bad token after the first 401 and retries anonymously, so charts/discover/trending keep working until the user updates the token

5.5.0 (2026-04-24) - settings reorganization
Settings reorganized into 3 user-friendly categories: Display / Playback / Account
Audio format options renamed to friendlier labels (Light Opus / Standard adaptive MP3 / Standard stable MP3)
"Tracks per page" replaces the old "Search items size" wording (used by both search and pagination)
Advanced API options (custom Client-ID, locale, search history size) moved to Expert level (use Kodi's Settings level slider to see them)

5.4.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed first card of each row being clipped on the left
Fixed orange focus border persisting on rows that no longer have focus (now only the focused row shows the orange highlight)
Fixed mini-player buttons rendering as empty squares (replaced Unicode chars with ASCII)
Fixed progress bar showing in cyan instead of orange (dedicated orange texture instead of colordiffuse)

5.4.0 (2026-04-24)
Home now has 4 configurable rows (Likes / Trending / Playlists / Following) in a vertically scrollable container
Each row can be configured/reordered/disabled in Settings > Home rows
Added pagination: pages now show a "Next page" item at the end when there are more results
Page size honors the existing "Items per page" setting
Selection now follows the playing track when autoplay moves to the next song
Mini-player has a new "Compact" mode (cover + title + wide progress bar, no controls)
Progress bar made thicker (8px) and properly themed in SoundCloud orange

5.3.0 (2026-04-24)
Removed "Classic interface" button from sidebar — switching back to the classic UI is now done via Settings > Interface > "Use the new interface" toggle (turn it off)
Sidebar now has 6 buttons: Home, Search, Likes, My playlists, Following, Settings

5.2.3 (2026-04-24)
Fixed all addon-localized labels using $ADDON[plugin.audio.soundcloud XXXXX] instead of $LOCALIZE[XXXXX] (which was looking up Kodi core strings, not ours)
Widened sidebar from 180px to 240px so French labels like "Vos abonnements" and "Interface classique" fit without truncation

5.2.2 (2026-04-24)
DIAGNOSTIC: hardcoded sidebar labels (no $LOCALIZE) to determine why text was invisible

5.2.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed all text being invisible in the new UI (sidebar buttons, page titles, mini-player labels): removed broken custom Font.xml and switched to Kodi's standard font names guaranteed by every skin

5.2.0 (2026-04-24)
Added auto-play next track: clicking a track now queues all visible tracks so Kodi plays them in sequence
Added "Auto-play next track" toggle in Settings > Interface (on by default)

5.1.4 (2026-04-24)
Fixed sidebar buttons appearing as solid white blocks (removed broken transparent texture)
Fixed last sidebar button being cut off by the mini-player (tightened vertical layout)

5.1.3 (2026-04-24)
Fixed sidebar text being invisible (explicit text positioning + better focus contrast)

5.1.2 (2026-04-24)
Fixed playback interruption caused by a window reload loop after auto-launching the new UI
Added re-entrancy guard to prevent stacking multiple WindowXML instances
Made focus assignment defensive (no more "Control X cannot focus" warnings)

5.1.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed audio decoder crash when SoundCloud transcoding URLs expire (now properly tells Kodi to skip the track instead of feeding it a None path)
Improved logging when stream URL resolution fails

5.1.0 (2026-04-24)
New full-screen interface (V2): sidebar navigation, horizontal carousel rows, mini-player with controls
Auto-launches by default — disable in Settings > Interface
Layout (rows-only or sidebar+rows) and mini-player mode (off/display/controls) configurable in Settings
Classic plugin still accessible via plugin://plugin.audio.soundcloud/?legacy=1 for widgets and fallback

5.0.3 (2026-04-24)
Fixed 404 on Mon profil sub-menus: api-v2 doesn't expose /me/* sub-resources, now resolves user_id via /me and uses /users/{id}/* paths

5.0.2 (2026-04-24)
Fixed crash on empty/non-JSON API responses (was crashing /me/* with JSONDecodeError on auth failure)
HTTP errors and empty bodies now return an empty collection and log a clear warning instead of crashing
401/403 responses now properly trigger the "OAuth token invalid or expired" notification

5.0.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed authenticated /me/* endpoints returning empty collections (no client_id when authenticated)
Fixed likes/reposts/playlist-likes envelope unwrapping for authenticated endpoints

4.3.0 (2026-04-24)
Added experimental full-screen UI (WindowXML script) with horizontal track carousel and mini-player
Launch via "New interface (beta)" from the root menu, or via RunScript(plugin.audio.soundcloud)

4.2.0 (2026-04-24)
Added optional OAuth token login to access likes, playlists, following and reposts
Added French translation
Added proper content types per view (songs/albums/artists) so skins pick the right layout
Added per-item fanart (artwork for tracks/playlists, profile banners for artists)
Added sort methods on song views (title, artist, duration, playcount)
Improved playlist and artist metadata (track count, follower count, mediatype)
Fixed crash on tracks without a display_date

4.1.0 (2025-10-06)
Fixed error when using addon
Added description and follower-counts to user profiles
Added description and likes to playlists
Added playcount to tracks
Updated Dutch translations

4.0.2 (2022-03-13)
Fixed random CloudFront errors when sending requests
Added context-menu option for removing search-history items

4.0.1 (2021-11-02)
Fixed error in "Discover"-folder

4.0.0 (2020-12-12)
Added support for Kodi v19 (Matrix)
        </news>
        <assets>
            <icon>resources/icon.png</icon>
            <fanart>resources/fanart.jpg</fanart>
        </assets>
    </extension>
</addon>
