<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<addon id="plugin.audio.soundcloud" name="SoundCloud" version="5.5.9" provider-name="jaylinski">
    <requires>
        <import addon="xbmc.python" version="3.0.0"/>
        <import addon="script.module.requests" version="2.29.0"/>
    </requires>
    <extension point="xbmc.python.pluginsource" library="addon.py">
        <provides>audio</provides>
    </extension>
    <extension point="xbmc.python.script" library="script.py">
        <provides>audio</provides>
    </extension>
    <extension point="xbmc.addon.metadata">
        <summary lang="de_DE">SoundCloud – Musik- und Podcast-Streaming-Plattform</summary>
        <summary lang="en_GB">SoundCloud – Music and podcast streaming platform</summary>
        <summary lang="fr_FR">SoundCloud – Plateforme de streaming musical et de podcasts</summary>
        <summary lang="nl_NL">SoundCloud – Muziek- en podcaststreamingplatform</summary>
        <description lang="de_DE">SoundCloud ist eine Musik- und Podcast-Streaming-Plattform, mit der Du Millionen von Songs aus der ganzen Welt anhören kannst.</description>
		<description lang="en_GB">SoundCloud is a music and podcast streaming platform that lets you listen to millions of songs from around the world.</description>
        <description lang="fr_FR">SoundCloud est une plateforme de streaming musical et de podcasts qui vous permet d'écouter des millions de titres du monde entier.</description>
        <description lang="nl_NL">SoundCloud is een muziek- en podcaststreamingplatform waarmee je naar miljoenen nummers van over de hele wereld kunt luisteren.</description>
        <disclaimer lang="en_GB">This plugin is not official, approved or endorsed by SoundCloud.</disclaimer>
        <disclaimer lang="fr_FR">Ce plugin n'est pas officiel, approuvé ou soutenu par SoundCloud.</disclaimer>
        <disclaimer lang="nl_NL">Deze plugin is niet officieel, goedgekeurd of gesteund door SoundCloud.</disclaimer>
        <platform>all</platform>
        <license>MIT</license>
        <forum>https://forum.kodi.tv/showthread.php?tid=206635</forum>
        <website>https://soundcloud.com</website>
        <source>https://github.com/jaylinski/kodi-addon-soundcloud</source>
        <credits>TheWorms</credits>
        <news>5.5.9 (2026-04-25)
Added TheWorms as a contributor (visible in Kodi's add-on info screen)

5.5.8 (2026-04-25) - progress bar fix
Fixed progress bar showing as fully filled and frozen: switched midtexture to use 9-patch border rendering and added explicit empty lefttexture/righttexture/overlaytexture so Kodi correctly interpolates the fill width
Resized orange.png from 4x4 to 8x8 so it survives the border="2" 9-patch slicing
Progress bar now shows in SoundCloud orange (#FF5500) and updates in real-time as the track plays

5.5.7 (2026-04-25)
Fixed: changes to OAuth token (or any setting) now take effect immediately without needing to restart Kodi
The Settings class now creates a fresh xbmcaddon.Addon() instance on every read, bypassing Kodi's in-memory cache that was hiding the new value
Auto-reset of the "token invalid" flag when the user changes the token — no more stuck 401 state after a paste

5.5.6 (2026-04-24) - diagnostic
"Test OAuth token" now shows the actual error body from SoundCloud (not just the HTTP code), and logs the full request + response details to kodi.log for debugging.

5.5.5 (2026-04-24)
OAuth token cleaning is now much more aggressive: strips ALL whitespace and non-printable characters anywhere in the token (not just leading/trailing). Catches Windows clipboard \r\n, zero-width spaces, BOM, etc. that were silently breaking authentication.
"Test OAuth token" now displays a token preview (length + first/last chars) so you can verify the paste was clean.

5.5.4 (2026-04-24)
Rewrote "How to get a token" help text — now correctly recommends the Authorization HTTP header (not the cookie). The cookie method silently fails, which is what was causing persistent 401 errors.

5.5.3 (2026-04-24)
After closing SoundCloud (Back), now go straight to Kodi home instead of bouncing back to the Music files / add-ons window
OAuth token field auto-strips "OAuth " or "Bearer " prefix if pasted by mistake (and surrounding quotes)

5.5.2 (2026-04-24)
Added "Test OAuth token" button in Settings > Account, right below the token field — verifies the token by calling /me and shows your username on success
Optimized /me handling: when the token is known invalid, skip the call entirely instead of doing 2 round-trips per UI page

5.5.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed cascade of HTTP 401 errors on public endpoints when an OAuth token is expired/invalid: the API now drops the bad token after the first 401 and retries anonymously, so charts/discover/trending keep working until the user updates the token

5.5.0 (2026-04-24) - settings reorganization
Settings reorganized into 3 user-friendly categories: Display / Playback / Account
Audio format options renamed to friendlier labels (Light Opus / Standard adaptive MP3 / Standard stable MP3)
"Tracks per page" replaces the old "Search items size" wording (used by both search and pagination)
Advanced API options (custom Client-ID, locale, search history size) moved to Expert level (use Kodi's Settings level slider to see them)

5.4.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed first card of each row being clipped on the left
Fixed orange focus border persisting on rows that no longer have focus (now only the focused row shows the orange highlight)
Fixed mini-player buttons rendering as empty squares (replaced Unicode chars with ASCII)
Fixed progress bar showing in cyan instead of orange (dedicated orange texture instead of colordiffuse)

5.4.0 (2026-04-24)
Home now has 4 configurable rows (Likes / Trending / Playlists / Following) in a vertically scrollable container
Each row can be configured/reordered/disabled in Settings > Home rows
Added pagination: pages now show a "Next page" item at the end when there are more results
Page size honors the existing "Items per page" setting
Selection now follows the playing track when autoplay moves to the next song
Mini-player has a new "Compact" mode (cover + title + wide progress bar, no controls)
Progress bar made thicker (8px) and properly themed in SoundCloud orange

5.3.0 (2026-04-24)
Removed "Classic interface" button from sidebar — switching back to the classic UI is now done via Settings > Interface > "Use the new interface" toggle (turn it off)
Sidebar now has 6 buttons: Home, Search, Likes, My playlists, Following, Settings

5.2.3 (2026-04-24)
Fixed all addon-localized labels using $ADDON[plugin.audio.soundcloud XXXXX] instead of $LOCALIZE[XXXXX] (which was looking up Kodi core strings, not ours)
Widened sidebar from 180px to 240px so French labels like "Vos abonnements" and "Interface classique" fit without truncation

5.2.2 (2026-04-24)
DIAGNOSTIC: hardcoded sidebar labels (no $LOCALIZE) to determine why text was invisible

5.2.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed all text being invisible in the new UI (sidebar buttons, page titles, mini-player labels): removed broken custom Font.xml and switched to Kodi's standard font names guaranteed by every skin

5.2.0 (2026-04-24)
Added auto-play next track: clicking a track now queues all visible tracks so Kodi plays them in sequence
Added "Auto-play next track" toggle in Settings > Interface (on by default)

5.1.4 (2026-04-24)
Fixed sidebar buttons appearing as solid white blocks (removed broken transparent texture)
Fixed last sidebar button being cut off by the mini-player (tightened vertical layout)

5.1.3 (2026-04-24)
Fixed sidebar text being invisible (explicit text positioning + better focus contrast)

5.1.2 (2026-04-24)
Fixed playback interruption caused by a window reload loop after auto-launching the new UI
Added re-entrancy guard to prevent stacking multiple WindowXML instances
Made focus assignment defensive (no more "Control X cannot focus" warnings)

5.1.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed audio decoder crash when SoundCloud transcoding URLs expire (now properly tells Kodi to skip the track instead of feeding it a None path)
Improved logging when stream URL resolution fails

5.1.0 (2026-04-24)
New full-screen interface (V2): sidebar navigation, horizontal carousel rows, mini-player with controls
Auto-launches by default — disable in Settings > Interface
Layout (rows-only or sidebar+rows) and mini-player mode (off/display/controls) configurable in Settings
Classic plugin still accessible via plugin://plugin.audio.soundcloud/?legacy=1 for widgets and fallback

5.0.3 (2026-04-24)
Fixed 404 on Mon profil sub-menus: api-v2 doesn't expose /me/* sub-resources, now resolves user_id via /me and uses /users/{id}/* paths

5.0.2 (2026-04-24)
Fixed crash on empty/non-JSON API responses (was crashing /me/* with JSONDecodeError on auth failure)
HTTP errors and empty bodies now return an empty collection and log a clear warning instead of crashing
401/403 responses now properly trigger the "OAuth token invalid or expired" notification

5.0.1 (2026-04-24)
Fixed authenticated /me/* endpoints returning empty collections (no client_id when authenticated)
Fixed likes/reposts/playlist-likes envelope unwrapping for authenticated endpoints

4.3.0 (2026-04-24)
Added experimental full-screen UI (WindowXML script) with horizontal track carousel and mini-player
Launch via "New interface (beta)" from the root menu, or via RunScript(plugin.audio.soundcloud)

4.2.0 (2026-04-24)
Added optional OAuth token login to access likes, playlists, following and reposts
Added French translation
Added proper content types per view (songs/albums/artists) so skins pick the right layout
Added per-item fanart (artwork for tracks/playlists, profile banners for artists)
Added sort methods on song views (title, artist, duration, playcount)
Improved playlist and artist metadata (track count, follower count, mediatype)
Fixed crash on tracks without a display_date

4.1.0 (2025-10-06)
Fixed error when using addon
Added description and follower-counts to user profiles
Added description and likes to playlists
Added playcount to tracks
Updated Dutch translations

4.0.2 (2022-03-13)
Fixed random CloudFront errors when sending requests
Added context-menu option for removing search-history items

4.0.1 (2021-11-02)
Fixed error in "Discover"-folder

4.0.0 (2020-12-12)
Added support for Kodi v19 (Matrix)
        </news>
        <assets>
            <icon>resources/icon.png</icon>
            <fanart>resources/fanart.jpg</fanart>
        </assets>
    </extension>
</addon>
